<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Code Colossus</title>
  <subtitle>Ben Hughes on Software</subtitle>
  <id>http://www.codecolossus.com/</id>
  <link href="http://www.codecolossus.com/"/>
  <link href="http://www.codecolossus.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2013-09-17T17:00:00-07:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Ben Hughes</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Coding on the Road</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/blog/2013/09/18/coding-on-the-road.html"/>
    <id>/blog/2013/09/18/coding-on-the-road.html</id>
    <published>2013-09-17T17:00:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2013-09-17T17:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Hughes</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;For the past four months I've been a digital nomad, traveling and working remotely from wherever I am. As a programmer, I'm grateful to do work that largely doesn't require a physical presence and for which bits traveling wirelessly earn me an income...&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For the past four months I've been a digital nomad, traveling and working remotely from wherever I am. As a programmer, I'm grateful to do work that largely doesn't require a physical presence and for which bits traveling wirelessly earn me an income. Though most folks claim it's an incredible time to be a programmer from a career perspective, I value the freedom/flexibility aspect of being a programmer in 2013 far more. I set out to take advantage of that freedom at the end of May, and haven't looked back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="image-container"&gt;
  &lt;img src="/blog/2013/09/18/coding-on-the-road/work_austin.jpg" /&gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
  &lt;img src="/blog/2013/09/18/coding-on-the-road/work_mission.jpg" /&gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
  &lt;img src="/blog/2013/09/18/coding-on-the-road/work_montana.jpg" /&gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, it's not all fun and games. Working on the road and in airports/airplanes comes with a host of challenges compared to your daily routine at home. Here's some issues I've run into and tips on how to be productive working while traveling:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="choosing-the-right-coffee-shop"&gt;Choosing the Right Coffee Shop&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you're in a new place, it can be hard to find a venue in which to camp out. I've been using mostly Foursquare Explore to search for coffee shops, which typically has lots of pictures from previous travelers. For me the pictures give the best indication of whether or not it might be work-friendly, and posted tips on the wifi also help. I aim for a local independent coffee shop with a medium-noise ambiance and some charm. Failing that, Starbucks is actually a great office-of-last-resort: they are virtually everywhere, have open tables available for camping, and have at least usable wifi most of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="unreliable-public-wifi"&gt;Unreliable Public WiFi&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As much as I often think we are "living in the future", I'm incredibly frustrated about the poor state of public wifi - whether paid or free. If a business advertises and offers "high-speed wifi with purchase", I think there's a reasonable expectation to have at least consistent latency below 150ms and throughput of 1mbps down. Many places don't even come close to this. It's an information assymmetry problem, because newcomers to a venue see the advertisement for free wifi (product bundling with paid goods) make purchasing decisions with this in mind, and incur a high degree of uncertainty whether it will work out or not. Here's what I do to avoid getting stuck with bad wifi:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have a speedtest application on your phone&lt;/strong&gt;, and check wifi quality before entering the venue and committing to buy something. This doesn't guarentee you're going to have a productive session, but you can at least weed our attrociously bad wifi beforehand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always have a back-up LTE tether.&lt;/strong&gt; I can't stress how important and freeing it is to always have a last-resort backup. Pretty much no matter where I am, I can tether to my phone and at least get something done, even if it's bandwidth-limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="coworking-drop-ins--day-rates"&gt;Coworking Drop-ins &amp;amp; Day Rates&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many coworking spaces will let you drop in for a day, either for free or for a small price. This is a good alternative to public wifi venues like coffee shops, and it increases your likelyhood of meeting new people and getting involved with the local community. The wifi issue above is also rarely an issue in coworking spots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="try-to-maintain-a-routine"&gt;Try to maintain a routine&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When traveling it's easy to get distracted and want to go do things. Be honest with yourself when your most productive time of the day is. For me it's the morning fueled with coffee, which also happens to be a time I'm least likely want to go out and explore, so this works perfectly. I get in the routine of waking up wherever I am and getting a solid four hours of work done, usually at a coffee shop. With this minimal routine, I'm assured to have a productive block of four hours each day. I then give myself more flexibility later in the day when I want to put more hours in, depending on what I want to explore or alternative uses of my time that evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="make-travel-plans-during-leisure-time-only"&gt;Make travel plans during leisure time only&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traveling nonstop means you'll spend a fair amount of time booking flights, finding hostels/hotels, and forming itineraries. It's easy to get drawn deeply into this and lose track of time. When you sit down to work, commit to work only - save travel planning for later at night or whenever your mind is less productive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="quiet-places-for-a-phone-call"&gt;Quiet Places for a Phone Call&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public places are noisy, and it can be difficult to find a place to just have a distraction-free phone call.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If staying a hotel, get 4PM late checkout.&lt;/strong&gt; This comes with elite status on some hotel chains, but even if you don't have status, it never hurts to ask. This guarentees you a quiet place to come back to for a phone call if you end up needing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consider a coworking spot with phone booths.&lt;/strong&gt; Not all of them have them, and they aren't great for long conversations, but it's often a decent place to hold a short call.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Selectively mute!&lt;/strong&gt; I've held many phone calls from noisy airports and coffee shops, and unless I'm the one doing most of the talking, being able to mute myself when I'm not talking allows for a more pleasant call.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If all else fails, consider wide open outside spaces.&lt;/strong&gt; I once held a phone call in the vast open space surrounding the Washington monument since I was staying a hostel with no quiet areas. An advantage of open spaces is that any noise is usually far away and far less audible over the phone. It's also easy to move out of the way if noise comes to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Call from your car.&lt;/strong&gt; A few times while working at a coffee shop I decided to just return to my car to hold a call. With tethering you can still be on the internet, at least temporarily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="working-on-airplanes"&gt;Working on Airplanes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love working on airplanes - I find them focus-inducing and lacking in any sort of distraction. The constant hum substitutes well for the coffee-shop background noise I crave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get a small laptop.&lt;/strong&gt; I could not live without my MacBook Air, which I feel comfortable working on in virtually any airplane seat. Being lightweight and mobile reduces the barriers to working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have a long-lasting battery.&lt;/strong&gt; With my 12 hour battery, it's nice never having to worry about plugging in. I can have a fully productive day, then plug in overnight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consider flying airlines with wifi.&lt;/strong&gt; Not all of them have it, but many do, and if you're going to be productive on a 6 hour flight, paying $20 really isn't so bad (or, consider a monthly subscription if you fly a lot). That being said, my most productive sessions are usually on planes &lt;strong&gt;without&lt;/strong&gt; wifi (no distractions!), so do realize this can be a double-edged sword.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="working-in-airports"&gt;Working in Airports&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With my mileage-running hobby, I spend a lot of time in airports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Choose your connection airports wisely.&lt;/strong&gt; Airports vary widely in friendlyness to working (outlets, quality wifi). If in JFK I'd much rather be in JetBlue T5 than any other terminal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get lounge access.&lt;/strong&gt; Having access to lounges makes airports far more bearable, and many have tiny working cubicles for establishing your own temporary office. I have lounge access many places through my American Express Platinum card, Priority Pass membership, and Star Alliance Gold status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Find gates without an upcoming flight.&lt;/strong&gt; Most gates show the next departure. It may be empty now, but if a flight is departing in 90 minutes, it will be busy and crowded. During non-peak hours many gates go unused for hours on end - find one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="dont-overwork"&gt;Don't overwork&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worst thing you can do is overwork yourself while traveling, because you're even more vulnerable to burn-out. Being active and busy with travel does not work well if you're having to put in 10 hour stressful days. Working while traveling works best doing 6-7 hours a day in productive spurts, mixed with some exploration. Always keep work-life balance in mind, and you'll find it's possible to work and travel successfully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="image-container"&gt;
  &lt;img src="/blog/2013/09/18/coding-on-the-road/work_plane.jpg" /&gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
  &lt;img src="/blog/2013/09/18/coding-on-the-road/work_tennis.jpg" /&gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I'm Leaving San Diego to Become a Nomad</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/blog/2013/05/18/leaving-san-diego-for-nomading-adventures.html"/>
    <id>/blog/2013/05/18/leaving-san-diego-for-nomading-adventures.html</id>
    <published>2013-05-17T17:00:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2013-05-17T17:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Hughes</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Two and a half years ago &lt;a href="/blog/2010/09/02/farewell-rochester-hello-san-diego.html"&gt;I left my home in Rochester and moved to San Diego, California&lt;/a&gt; on a whim, in search of new experiences. In that time, I've gotten to know so many wonderful people and really fell in love with the city. As a good friend here...&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Two and a half years ago &lt;a href="/blog/2010/09/02/farewell-rochester-hello-san-diego.html"&gt;I left my home in Rochester and moved to San Diego, California&lt;/a&gt; on a whim, in search of new experiences. In that time, I've gotten to know so many wonderful people and really fell in love with the city. As a good friend here likes to say, "San Diego isn't outstanding at any one thing, but is above average at almost all things", and I completely agree. San Diego really is a great city, and one I will never hesitate to come back to frequently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But during the past few years, I've gotten bitten hard by wanderlust and began doing a lot more traveling. I've had the opportunity to visit many great cities, but usually only for a few days at a time. When leaving each one, I can't help but feel that I should spend more time there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so that's what I'll be doing. Starting June 1st, I'm leaving my apartment in San Diego, getting rid of the few belongings I do have, and set out with my car to become a nomad for the next seven months. While my plans aren't entirely certain, and I don't really want them to be, I hope to spend at least a few weeks each in: &lt;strong&gt;San Francisco, Portland, Seattle, Denver/Boulder, Chicago, Rochester/Buffalo, Sydney/Melbourne, Hong Kong, and Austin&lt;/strong&gt;. In the midst of driving around the country I'll also spend a few days in some smaller cities like Boise, and I've also got some international trips planned to finally make use of the airline miles I've been accumulating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'll be working during the day doing consulting for remote clients just as I do now, hopefully exploring new coworking spaces in these cities and getting involved as much as possible in the local developer community. I plan to stay mostly in shared Airbnb apartments with the occasional staying-with-friends mixed in when possible. I'll also be driving a lot from place to place, and probably flying quite a bit (including back to San Diego with some frequency).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While embarking on this new adventure is exciting, it's also scary. Settling into these new cities with no friends will be hard, and constantly moving will strain any real relationships I do make there. But I ultimately hope to meet a lot of great people, have some interesting experiences, feel what living in some of these cities is like, and hopefully choose a place to settle down more permanently once the nomading is over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'll deeply miss my friends in San Diego, but know that I'll be back often and this isn't goodbye for long. Moving to San Diego over two years ago was one of the best decisions I made, and I was scared then - but I went for it. I think now's the time in my life to get out there and see the world, and I'm not turning back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to follow my travels, I'll be photo blogging at &lt;a href="http://travel.benhughes.name"&gt;http://travel.benhughes.name&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>My Goals as a Programmer for 2013</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/blog/2013/01/13/goals-as-a-programmer-for-2013.html"/>
    <id>/blog/2013/01/13/goals-as-a-programmer-for-2013.html</id>
    <published>2013-01-12T16:00:00-08:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-12T16:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Hughes</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Though ultimately it's a date no different from any other - and entirely arbitrary - New Years Eve has always been a great time for me to reflect on what I'm doing with my life, and re-calibrate my goals. Though I have other "life goals" outside the...&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Though ultimately it's a date no different from any other - and entirely arbitrary - New Years Eve has always been a great time for me to reflect on what I'm doing with my life, and re-calibrate my goals. Though I have other "life goals" outside the realm of programming, here's what I want to focus on in 2013 with respect to programming:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="blog-more"&gt;Blog More&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog has been mostly dead for the past few years, which is deplorable. I find blogging, and the organization of thoughts that go with it, a great activity for improving mental clarity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="work-on-a-travel-related-application-im-passionate-about"&gt;Work on a travel-related application I'm passionate about&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My passions changes frequently, but at the moment I'm really passionate about travel. I'd really love to be working on an awesome travel-related web application. Loving what you're working on is important for career hapiness!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="cowork--pair-with-awesome-developers"&gt;Cowork / Pair with Awesome Developers&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working remotely in San Diego leaves me lonely sometimes. I need to get out and do more coworking and pairing with other developers who I can learn from and who will challenge me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="finish-jazzity-my-long-delayed-knowledge-engine-for-jazz-theory"&gt;Finish Jazzity, my long-delayed knowledge engine for jazz theory&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started playing around with jazz theory relationships in code five years ago, starting out with a simple ruby library with object relationships. Since then I've been building out a more fleshed out web application that lets users query and interact with jazz theory through a web brwoser, not unlike what WolframAlpha is trying to do for generalized knowledge. The recent availability of VexFlow, an awesome HTML5 SVG music staff notation engraving library is really opening up the possibilties to build something awesome. In 2013 I want to finish and launch Jazzity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="contribute-more-actively-to-open-source"&gt;Contribute more actively to open source&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to work fairly actively on my own open source projects, but beyond the occassional collaboration to the SDRuby.org, rarely have I truly collaborated with others on an important open source project. I want to find some projects I use heavily and contribute back!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="become-a-master-at-vim"&gt;Become a Master at vim&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My editing environment is MacVim (using tabs, with splits within tabs for implementation/test code), and although I can get around in vim quite fluently, there are a lot of advanced vim features I want to learn. Seeing Ben Orenstein's talk at RubyConf and his vim fluency has inspired me to learn more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="become-comfortable-with-sublimetext2"&gt;Become Comfortable with SublimeText2&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though I'm solidly a vim user, I've heard great things about SublimeText. I loved TextMate "back in the day", and want to give SublimeText a fair shake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="learn-d3js-and-build-something-awesome-with-it"&gt;Learn D3.js and Build Something Awesome with It&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data and statistics have always interested me, and D3.js is a really unique approach on working with data in JavaScript. I've seem some awesome stuff built with it, and I'd like to learn D3 better and apply it to something I'm passionate about (probably something in the realm of economics).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="learn-rubymotion-and-build-a-simple-ios-application"&gt;Learn RubyMotion and Build a simple iOS Application&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've really missed the mobile native app revolution entirely, and it's time to catch up. I've heard good things about RubyMotion, so starting there (after learning basic Objective C for some foundation, of coures) sounds like a great way to dive in. My goal is to get an application (however simple and useless) approved in the Apple app store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="learn-scala--clojure"&gt;Learn Scala &amp;amp; Clojure&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning new programming languages is one of the best ways to keep yourself current and push the limits of your knowledge. Learning Ruby was a real paradigm shift for me (coming from a PHP/Java background), and the programming/concurrency models of more functional languages intrigues me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="improve-designcss-chops"&gt;Improve Design/CSS Chops&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I'm working on a few personal applications (like Jazzity), I really should be better at front-end design than I am. I actually enjoy crafting good HTML and CSS, but having a good design concept to begin with is where I struggle. I'd like to try to change that, while at the same time accepting that I am a focused back-end developer with limited creative juices for design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="spend-more-time-in-tech-heavy-cities-and-possibly-move-to-one"&gt;Spend more time in tech-heavy cities (and possibly move to one…)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've been extremely happy with my move to San Diego, but I think it's time to explore cities with a larger tech scene. In 2013 I'd like to spend a lot more time in cities like San Francisco, Portland, Seattle, Chicago, Austin, Boulder, and New York - and possibly move to one!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="attend-2-4-regional-conferences-and-one-international-conference"&gt;Attend 2-4 Regional Conferences, and One International Conference&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus far I have only ever attended large Ruby conferences, yet I hear from so many people that the regional conferences are the best (and the most affordable for someone who pays out-of-pocket!). Especially since no one has to pull my leg to board an airplane, I'd like to travel to 2-4 regional conferences and one conference outside the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Using ActiveModel::Name to simplify URL generation</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/blog/2011/05/01/active-model-name-and-resources.html"/>
    <id>/blog/2011/05/01/active-model-name-and-resources.html</id>
    <published>2011-04-30T17:00:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2011-04-30T17:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Hughes</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Most Rails developers are familiar with generating RESTful URLs polymorphically by simply passing an object to one of many helper methods that expects a URL, such as link_to and form_for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# In Routes
resources :articles

# In View:
form_for @article...&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Most Rails developers are familiar with generating RESTful URLs polymorphically by simply passing an object to one of many helper methods that expects a URL, such as link_to and form_for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# In Routes
resources :articles

# In View:
form_for @article do |f|
This capability extends beyond just single objects, supporting nested routes and specific action targeting; for example:

# In Routes:
namespace :admin do
  resources :categories do
    resources :articles
  end
end

# In View
form_for [:admin, @category, @article] do |f|
end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id="problem"&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One problem I've run into with some frequency, however, is using this polymorphic path approach when the class name of the ActiveRecord model does not quite correspond directly with the resource name. This occurs most frequently when you want a little more context in your model naming which may not be necessary in routes. For example, lets look a domain model with customers having many customer locations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Models:
class Customer &amp;lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  has_many :locations, :class_name =&amp;gt; "CustomerLocation"
end

class CustomerLocation &amp;lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  belongs_to :customer
end

# Routes:
resources :customers do
  resources :locations
end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the above example, the model name is "CustomerLocation", but the resource name as specified in the routes is just "locations", since the context of customers is already well-established from the nesting. The problem with this is when we try to use our regular polymorphic path solution:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;form_for [@customer, @location]
# Tries to generate: customer_customer_location_path(@customer, @location)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people when running into this will just do away with using the clean polymorphic path solution entirely and instead provide the URL explicitly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;form_for @location, :url =&amp;gt; customer_location_path(@customer, @location)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This of course works but isn't exactly ideal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="solution"&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it might look like it's using the class name to construct the url helper method name, it's in fact using "model_name" instead (which defaults to the class name). But, this can be overridden!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;class CustomerLocation &amp;lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  def self.model_name
    ActiveModel::Name.new("Location")
  end
end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this, the polymorphic path [@customer, @location] works as we would expect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another common situation where this technique becomes useful is if you are working extensively with namespaced models. This is tricky because the namespace ends up becoming part of the model name, which almost surely does not map to your resource hierarchy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Model:
class Core::Customer &amp;lt; Core::Base
end

# View:
form_for @customer
# Tries to generate: core_customer_path(@customer)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overriding model_name will allow you to explicitly define "Customer" as the model name, despite it being namespaced within "Core". But we can do better than that - if you have a base model for your namespace (as I believe is always a good practice), just put this in the base model:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;class Core::Base &amp;lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  def self.model_name
    ActiveModel::Name.new(name.split("::").last)
  end
end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this technique has served me well in many apps, do be aware that the model name is used in some other instances throughout Rails such as error_messages_for, so do use this with care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though all of the above examples are for ActiveModel/ActiveRecord 3.0 or higher, the same technique will work in Rails 2.3 by simply using "ActiveSupport::ModelName" in place of "ActiveModel::Name".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="update"&gt;Update&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Rails 3.1 and higher it seems the solution is now:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;class CustomerLocation &amp;lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  def self.model_name
    ActiveModel::Name.new(self, nil, "Location")
  end
end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why you should always validate maximum lengths in models, and how to do so easily</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/blog/2011/01/01/validates-lengths-from-database.html"/>
    <id>/blog/2011/01/01/validates-lengths-from-database.html</id>
    <published>2010-12-31T16:00:00-08:00</published>
    <updated>2010-12-31T16:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Hughes</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Developers seem to rarely use validates_lengths_of with their models, despite there being an inherent maximum length on every string and text field - the one enforced by the database. Since table migrations in Rails set a fairly high maximum length...&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Developers seem to rarely use validates_lengths_of with their models, despite there being an inherent maximum length on every string and text field - the one enforced by the database. Since table migrations in Rails set a fairly high maximum length for string attributes, most people don't think twice about the possibly of that limit being exhausted. Even beyond this, there may be other reasons why the field limit is set fairly low, or perhaps you're working with a legacy database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without validating maximum field lengths at the model level, ActiveRecord will still ship off the full field value as entered in an INSERT query. From there two things might happen, and this depends on the database itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It might fail the query with an ActiveRecord::StatementInvalid exception. Since this is an exception most developers don't routinely handle, this could cause the entire request to fail. This occurs with SQL Server for sure, and possibly other databases.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It might accept the query and simply truncate the result to the field limit. This might sound better than #1, but IMO it's actually worse: now you have an instance where the everything appeared to go along fine, but you might end up with missing data. This is the default behavior with MySQL.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There's another reason why you should always validate field lengths, and that's to limit the possibilities for a Denial of Service attack. If an attacker knows you aren't validating field length and that whatever they're providing is going straight into an SQL query and being sent to the database, they can craft extremely large requests that might fill up the pipe to the database. Even if the data doesn't actually end up being inserted in full, they've tied up a database connection and - since the regular old "mysql" gem will block for the query result - a Rails process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately in order to do this properly you essentially have to write validates_length_of lines (or the equivalent ActiveRecord 3 form) for each attribute, with it's maximum database length. To make this easy, I wrote a gem called validates_lengths_from_database that will introspect your database string field maximum lengths and automatically defines length validations for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To install, just include the gem in your Gemfile (works with Rails 2.3 and Rails 3.0):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;gem "validates_lengths_from_database"
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then in your model you can activate validations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;class Post &amp;lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  validates_lengths_from_database
end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also supports filter-style :only and :except options:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;class Post &amp;lt; ActiveRecord::Base     validates_lengths_from_database :only =&amp;gt; [:title, :contents]
end

class Post &amp;lt; ActiveRecord::Base     validates_lengths_from_database :except =&amp;gt; [:other_field]
end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that this cannot be done at a global level directly against ActiveRecord::Base, since the validates_length_from_database method requires the class to have a table name (with the ability to load the schema).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information or to view the source, check out the project on GitHub: &lt;a href="http://github.com/rubiety/validates_lengths_from_database"&gt;validates_lengths_from_database&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Farewell Rochester, Hello San Diego</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/blog/2010/09/02/farewell-rochester-hello-san-diego.html"/>
    <id>/blog/2010/09/02/farewell-rochester-hello-san-diego.html</id>
    <published>2010-09-01T17:00:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2010-09-01T17:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Hughes</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Six years ago I moved to Rochester, a city that at the time I had only vague recognition of, to start my life as a college student at RIT.  In those past six years I've gotten to know and grown to like the city I began my "adult life" in, despite the...&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Six years ago I moved to Rochester, a city that at the time I had only vague recognition of, to start my life as a college student at RIT.  In those past six years I've gotten to know and grown to like the city I began my "adult life" in, despite the horrid winters.  Having grown personally a great deal in Rochester over the past six years, I've come to consider Rochester my "home" (over my parents' home in Williamsport, PA).  After college, I decided to continue working independently based out of Rochester to do freelancing full-time.  Since then I've had the opportunity to meet and work with many great people, especially at Coworking Rochester, who have greatly enriched my daily life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, the past nine months have had me itching for a change.  Many of my college friends have moved on, and somehow there seems like there's less for me in Rochester than there was when I was a college student.  The winters are also a depressing time of year when I feel like I'm only able to live half of my life.  I have visited many cities in the US and gotten to experience what life in another city might be like.  Most of all, I really just feel like taking a chance on something new - a new adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, after several trips there and much deliberation, I have decided to move to San Diego in November.  There are several reasons why I chose San Diego:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;San Diego is a "big city".  I've always longed to live in a larger city where more opportunities of all kinds await.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;San Diego weather is outstanding.  Being able to play tennis every single day is a major plus.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;San Diego has a lot of charm, particularly in the many communities outside of downtown such as North Park and Hillcrest.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My parents are moving (for half of the year) to Palm Springs, a city only a couple hours away.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Although paling in size to San Francisco, San Diego seems to have a decent tech community (and Ruby community).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The entire area seems far more laid back, and people are friendlier.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I do actually know a few people out there, which is more than I can see for most west coast cities.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I am in the process of shedding almost all of my personal belongings. Before I leave, my property will consist of my keyboard (piano), some clothes, and my laptop.  On November 5th I will begin the drive out to San Diego, stopping in RubyConf in New Orleans along the way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conjunction with this move I'll also be doing quite a bit of traveling between now and November 5th when I begin the drive out.  For part of September I'll be taking advantage of the JetBlue All You Can Jet pass to visit Chicago, Boston, Washington DC, Seattle, Portland, San Francisco, Los Angeles, San Diego, and Phoenix, not mainly to tour but to just be in a different city each day and take in the vibe.  During this trip I'll be working more or less like normal.  After that, and since my apartment lease ends September 30th, I'll be spending the month of October "homeless" on an around-the-world trip patched together with cheap flights and hostel stays.  On this trip I'll be starting in San Diego to look for apartments, then flying around the world westward to Vancouver, Hong Kong, Singapore, Bangkok, Dubai, Abu Dhabi, Istanbul, Athens, Barcelona, and finally New York.  I've scheduled a few days in each city and will be trying to see as much as possible.  I'm absolutely stoked about these two trips since I have such a huge passion for travel.  I doubt the low-cost opportunities that have made these trips so extremely cheap and affordable by me will ever come about again.
During these two trips I'll be blogging along the way and maintaining a travel journal at Everlater:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.everlater.com/benhughes/commuting-to-the-west-coast-on-jetblue-aycj"&gt;JetBlue All-You-Can-Jet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.everlater.com/benhughes/around-the-world-westward"&gt;Around the World Trip&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the next 2 months I will be flying 54,000 miles - over twice the circumference of Earth - and driving over 3,000 miles on what is by far the biggest adventure I've ever been on.  This exciting trip will be a great "reset" before I start to rebuild my life in a new city.  Despite this, the move will also be stressful and challenging for many weeks as I get settled into San Diego and start to meet new people, something I don't always have an easy time doing.  Though challenging, I think it will be worth it in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To all of my friends in Rochester: you will be missed.  Thank you for the great past several years.  I'll be back from time to time, and if you're ever out in the San Diego area - do let me know!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
